<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of carefulness wherein is set forth the symptomes of dangers by arguments against means to prevent overcharging cares. By the late faithfull preacher of Gods Word, Henry Archer, sometimes preacher in London.</title>
            <author>Archer, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899553</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153805</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153805)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2380:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of carefulness wherein is set forth the symptomes of dangers by arguments against means to prevent overcharging cares. By the late faithfull preacher of Gods Word, Henry Archer, sometimes preacher in London.</title>
                  <author>Archer, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 138 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R. Bishop for Francis Coles, at the halfe Bowle in the Old Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "symptomes of ... means to prevent" are joined together by a left and a right brace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Congregational Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153805:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF Carefulneſs; Wherein is ſet forth The
<list>
                  <item>Symptomes of</item>
                  <item>Dangers by</item>
                  <item>Arguments againſt</item>
                  <item>Means to prevent</item>
               </list> overcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cares.</p>
            <p>By the late faithfull Preacher of Gods Word, HENRY ARCHER, Sometimes Preacher in London.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 7.32.</bibl>
               <p>But I would have you without, carefulneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop</hi> for <hi>Francis Coles,</hi> at the halfe Bowle in the Old Baily, 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153805:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153805:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne generation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and another generation ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth</hi> (ſaith the Wiſeman.) In the revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a few years, the earth is delivered of her former bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and another crop of men and creatures ſpring up. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>naturall</hi> parts, <hi>morall</hi> gifts, nor <hi>ſpirituall</hi> graces will availe againſt that peremptory ſentence, <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt return.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Prophets, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:153805:3"/> ſaith, <hi>Where are they? Moſes,</hi> though <hi>a man of God,</hi> a <hi>meek</hi> man, and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> yet he muſt <hi>goe up into the Mount and die;</hi> and then, <hi>Ariſe</hi> Ioſhuah, (ſaith God) <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>ſervant</hi> of God, and <hi>Miniſter</hi> of Chriſt, having ſome years ſince taſted of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; though he left a name behinde him, <hi>as the ſmell of Lebanon,</hi> (being in his life time faithfull and painfull in Gods harveſt:) yet things committed onely to memory, being in ſhort time forgotten, I thought it not unfit (partly for the preſervation of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall, and partly for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the preſent and future times) to erect this little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument (as it was hewed by himſelfe) upon his grave.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153805:3"/>
            <p>This preſent Treatiſe, among many of his fruitfull labours, as it is not unfit for any time, ſo it may be eſteemed moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in theſe anxious dayes, wherein the hearts of men are generally eaten up with immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate cares about future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, both nationall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, whereby the lives of men become wholly uncomfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and they become ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tormentors. The worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour herein hath clearly and fully diſcovered, the cauſes, ſymptomes, dangers, &amp; effects, with the remedies of this needleſſe, bootleſſe, pernicious evill of carking cares, which as a lethall ſpring, drieth up the ſtrength of the ſpirits.</p>
            <p>I will not wrong the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour ſo much, or detaine the Reader ſo long, as by a perfun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory
<pb facs="tcp:153805:4"/> commendation, to ſet forth a thing of ſuch worth. I rather refer the Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Treatiſe it ſelfe, wherein thou ſhalt finde the ſcope to disburthen thy heart of wordly cares, and to bring it into perfect tranquility; which as it is the intent of the work, ſo it is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Chriſtian friend, <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153805:4"/>
            <head>A TREATISE of CAREFVLNES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LUKE 21.34.</bibl>
                  <p>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeting and drunkenneſſe, and the cares of this life, and that day come upon you unawares.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>And Cares of this life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Saviour in this Verſe, by way of exhortation, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a notable meanes by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153805:5"/> which his Diſciples might be prepared for the time of judgement, whenſoever it ſhould come; that is, by taking heed of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of their hearts ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>with ſurfeting, or drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, or the cares of this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus it is ſet forth by the time wherein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to avoid this overcharging, that is, at all times, <hi>Leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo it is expreſt by a motive, <hi>Leſt that day come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you unawares.</hi> If your hearts at any time be overcharged, then might the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>come upon you unawares.</hi> As therefore they deſired that the time of judgement ſhould not come upon them unawares, ſo they muſt bee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153805:5"/> carefull that at no time their hearts were overcharged.</p>
            <p>The overcharging that ſhould be avoided, is of two ſorts;
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>ſurfeting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>the cares of this life.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that their hearts were not <hi>overcharged with ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drunkenneſſe,</hi> which by a Synecdoche doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and import all kinde of pleaſures and contentments of this preſent world, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfull or unlawfull. The point that wee might obſerve hence is this, that
<q>The people that would not have the time of judgement come upon them unawares or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153805:6"/> muſt be very carefull that at no time their hearts be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or pleaſures of this world, either law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or unlawfull.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But that which I meane to ſtand upon, is the ſecond thing, that people muſt take heed they be not overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall, that is, <hi>The cares of this life.</hi> It is not enough for people to take heed that they be not overcharged with pleaſures, but alſo to take heed leſt they be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with cares.</p>
            <p>In the opening of this you may conſider what cares are in the generall. <note place="margin">Care, what.</note> Care, it is the applying of the minde to thinke upon ſome object with regard to it, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153805:6"/> you have it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.14. <note place="margin">Mat. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter thou careſt not for any man, neither regardeſt thou the perſon of any man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if you will, Care is an earneſt intention of minde, or of ſtudy for the obtaining of ſomewhat. When the minde is earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent and imployed upon the obtaining of ſomething, it is fitly called Care.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of cares</note> Now Care in Scripture is diſtinguiſhed by the object of it; as here in the Text, <hi>The cares of this life;</hi> it implies that there are cares of another life: So in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.22. <note place="margin">Mat. 13.22.</note> it is called the cares of this world; it ſuppoſeth that there are cares for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world. When Care is about the things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this preſent life, then it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153805:7"/> is called care of this life, or care of this world. When the Care is about the things of the world to come, then it is called heavenly Care, or Care of the world to come.</p>
            <p>That that is here meant in the Text, as the Text it ſelfe ſhewes, is the Care of this life. Now our Saviour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them not from the Care of this life, but from being overtaken with the Cares of this life, <hi>Take heed leſt your hearts be overcharged with the cares of this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Care pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, what.</note> Care for this life ſimply is not prohibited, but the overcharging Care, that Care that overchargeth the heart. And by this we may be able to underſtand the meaning of thoſe Scriptures that ſeeme to prohibite all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153805:7"/> kinde of Care, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Take no thought what you ſhall eat or drinke,</hi> &amp;c. So in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <note place="margin">Phil 4.</note> 
               <hi>be carefull in nothing</hi> And that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>I would have you be without careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Many ſuch Scriptures there are that prohibite all kinde of Care ſeemingly. But this will helpe us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the meaning of them; for it cannot bee meant of the prohibition of all Care, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in another place gives us command to care for the things of this world. So in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>The fathers ſhould lay up for the children, and not the children for the fathers.</hi> So in <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6. <note place="margin">Prov. 6.6.</note> we are bid to learne diligence and care of the Ant or Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, that in Summer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153805:8"/> for Winter. And we finde diligence, and care, and painfulneſſe, to be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly preſt, and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſt in Scripture, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot be meant of a prohibition ſimply of all care. But I ſay the Text helps us to reconcile theſe Scriptures: Some Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay, <hi>Care not for the things of this life;</hi> others ſay, <hi>care for them;</hi> that is, Care not too much for the things of this life; Care not ſo as to have your hearts over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the cares of this preſent life. This I note by the way in the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words, becauſe it is a good explication and reconciliation of theſe texts. <hi>Let not your hearts be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the cares of this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153805:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Not only caring for overmuch, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much care for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things forbidden.</note> Our Saviour ſeemes here to bid us take heed of being overcharged with the Care of the neceſſaries and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: for in that he ſaith <hi>the cares of this life,</hi> hee ſeemes directly to expreſſe ſuch things as are neceſſary and very convenient for this preſent life. Hee ſaith not, Let not your hearts be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care for <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities</hi> and <hi>abundance</hi> of this preſent life; but <hi>Let not your hearts be overcharged with the cares of this preſent life,</hi> with the care of thoſe things that are neceſſary and very convenient for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life; take heed that your hearts be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, no not with thoſe cares. It is not enough for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153805:9"/> a Chriſtian that he be not overcharged with care for ſuperfluities, but that he be not overcharged with care for neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>And that this is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, it ſeemes to bee expreſt in <hi>Luke</hi> 8.14. <note place="margin">Luk. 8.14.</note> where our Saviour ſpeaking of Care, he mentions Care and Riches together, making them diſtinct things. Thoſe which fell among thornes, are thoſe which fell among Pleaſures and Riches, and Cares of this life. Chriſt makes a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Cares, Riches, and Pleaſures, intimating that <hi>Cares</hi> as well as <hi>Riches</hi> choak the Word. Care for neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and conveniences, as well as care of abundance, and the having of it; the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153805:9"/> labouring to get much: the one as well as the other choak the Word. And thereupon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.25.</note> our Saviour prohibiting the overcharging care, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in neceſſaries, not in abundance and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluites; <hi>take no thought for your life,</hi> be not overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with care and thought concerning your life, <hi>what yee ſhall eat or drinke, and wherewith ye ſhall be cloathed.</hi> He not onely bids us take heed that wee bee not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with Care for abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, but for neceſſaries, even for our life, in regard of neceſſary food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And this I take to be the meaning here in the Text, <hi>Let not your hearts be overcharged with the cares of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153805:10"/> this life:</hi> take heed of being overcharged with cares for neceſſaries, and with thoſe things that are very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for this preſent life.</p>
            <p>I pray obſerve it, it is not onely the duty of people, that they care not for too much, but to have a care that they care not too much for any thing. Not onely muſt they be carefull not to care for abundance, how to heap up gold and ſilver as the ſands on the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore; but they muſt take heed of caring too much for the neceſſaries and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of this preſent life. There is not onely an errour, when they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their hearts with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for abundance; but though that they care for be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153805:10"/> never ſo little and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient or neceſſary, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding if they care too much for that, they overcharge the heart, they unfit and unprepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the time of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; this I take to be the meaning of this exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Let not your hearts be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged,</hi> no not <hi>with the cares of this preſent life.</hi> The Doctrine the words afford us is thus much;
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Too much care for neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries unfits for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> The people that would not have judgement come upon them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared and unawares, muſt be carefull at all times that they never be overcharged with too much care for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this preſent life.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153805:11"/>
            <p>How ever it be lawfull to care for the neceſſaries and conveniences of this life, yet it is not lawfull to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the heart with care for them. It is lawfull for a man to eat meat, but it is not lawfull to overcharge his ſtomack too much. It is lawfull for a man to drinke drinke, but not to overcharge himſelfe too much. It is lawfull for a man to lay upon his ſervants back a burden, but not to overcharge his ſervants back with too great a burden. So, however it be lawful for peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to care for this life, for the neceſſaries and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of this preſent world, yet it is not lawfull to care too much to overcharge the heart with too much care
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153805:11"/> for the things of this life. That is the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the heart, what.</note> For the opening of it, we may conſider what it is to overcharge the heart.</p>
            <p>It is a metaphor taken from overcharging of the ſtomack with more meat and drink than the ſtomack can take or digeſt well. Or to overcharge the back with a heavier burden than it can well beare. So when there is more care for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conveniences and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries than the heart can well demeane it ſelfe under as befits and becomes it: this is the overcharging of the heart.</p>
            <p>Now that you may the better underſtand what this overcharging of the heart is, you ſhall know it by theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153805:12"/> evidences and ſymptomes. <note place="margin">Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the heart.</note> The heart appeares to bee overcharged with too much care, when theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex and diſquiet it.</note> Firſt, when the heart is oppreſſed and diſtracted, perplexed and diſquieted with care, when it ſinks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care, and is overburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the ſpirit comes to droop under the care, that is a ſigne the heart cares too much, that it is overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, what ever the things are for which it cares. Though they be never ſo convenient and neceſſary it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is a ſure ſigne that the heart is overcharged with too much care, when care comes to diſtract and diſquiet, and perplex the ſoule. So indeed the word
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153805:12"/> in the originall ſignifies a kinde of dividing and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſunder of the ſoule; as by the diſſolution of any member of the body there comes to be paine, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and anguiſh in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>This is expreſſed to us in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.23. <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>For all his dayes are ſorrow, and travell, and griefe, his heart takes not reſt in the night. This alſo is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Here is a heart over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care, when in the day time he is full of ſorrow, and in the night time his ſpirit takes no reſt. Now there are two things by which uſually the ſpirit is thus perplexed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 By feare of want.</note> The one, when it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with diſtruſtfull fear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153805:13"/> of want and neceſſity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it may fall in hard times, and in time to come. When the heart ſo cares for proviſion of food and raiment, or other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, either for it ſelfe, or thoſe that belong to us; as that for feare of want and miſery, and neceſſity that may come upon us, it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed and diſquieted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 By doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</note> Or elſe when the heart is perplexed with ſolicitouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d anxious ſuſpence, doubting about the event and iſſue of a lawfull courſe that a man takes for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of neceſſaries. This is it you have in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.29. <note place="margin">Luk. 12.29.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke not what ye ſhall eat and drink.</hi> Is that unlawfull? No; but ſeeke it not ſo as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and perplex your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153805:13"/> with doubt, whether the meanes, and the paines and labour you take, will have ſo good effect as to provide neceſſaries for you or no. That that is the meaning of it, appeares by the next words, <hi>neither be of a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full minde,</hi> that is, in care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſuſpence. When the heart of man ſo cares for neceſſaries, and labours in the uſe of lawfull meanes that God hath appointed, that it is in doubtfull ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence, and ſo anxious and diſtruſtfull, and ſolicitous about the event, whether this or that courſe will take effect, whether it will have ſuch an event and effect as he expects; when the heart perplexeth it ſelfe about the iſſue, and iſſue of its la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153805:14"/> and meanes, this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>It is a very bold thing for any heart to take carefull thought about the event of things that belong to God. It is our duty to uſe the meanes to walke in the way of God, and in ſo doing, to commit our ſelves to the bleſſing of God. That is the meaning of that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.4.</note> 
               <hi>Commit thy way to God.</hi> Uſe the meanes that God hath appointed, but leave the iſſue and event to God. And that alſo is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Scriptures, both in the <hi>Philippians,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for nothing:</hi> And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Caſt your care on the Lord.</hi> Uſe the meanes and leave the event and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and bleſſing to the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153805:14"/>
            <p>Thus did <hi>Saul</hi> erre, when he was about to prepare his Army to goe to battell with the Philiſtines, hee was anxious and ſolicitous about the event, and ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the victory, that he perplexed and diſquieted his ſpirit with diſtruſtfull thoughts what the iſſue of that battell would be. And it was the ſin of that King, in 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">1 King. 2.</note> when he was ſick, he ſent to enquire of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren gods, whether he ſhould recover of his ſickneſſe. He was ſolicitous about the event, and thereupon his ſpirit was perplexed and diſquieted. Here is the firſt ſymptome of a heart over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care, even for neceſſaries: when it ſo cares that the heart is divided, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153805:15"/> the ſpirit is perplexed, that the ſoule droops under thought, with ſuſpence and anxious ſolicitouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the event.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Too much care for the future.</note> A ſecond ſymptome of a heart overcharged with care, is this; when the heart not only cares for neceſſaries for the preſent, but for the future: When the heart cares not only for to day, but for to morrow. The object of our care is to day, the preſent time, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread.</hi> He that cares though but for neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not onely for bread to day, but for bread to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, hee takes more care than God hath appointed. How ſpeaks our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> 
               <hi>Take therefore no thought for the morrow.</hi> Hee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153805:15"/> then that takes thought not only for to day, but for to morrow, he takes thought too much, and his heart muſt needs be oppreſt and overcharged with care. For why, obſerve our Saviours reaſon, <hi>ſufficient for the day is the evill thereof.</hi> The care of the preſent day brings ſorrow and burthen, and weight enough. Who ever hath but the care of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time upon his backe, hath as much as he can bear: he that therefore takes in care for the future time alſo, he muſt needs overburthen his back, and lay too great a load on him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All care for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not unlawfull</note> Not (beloved) that it is altogether unlawfull for a man to provide for the time to come. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſends us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153805:16"/> to the Ant, to the Piſmire, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. <note place="margin">Pro. 6.</note> that in Summer layes up for Winter. And you ſhall finde <hi>Ioſephs</hi> wiſdome in Egypt, in the yeares of plenty he provided for the yeares of famine to come after. And in <hi>Act.</hi> 11. the three laſt verſes, <note place="margin">Act. 11.</note> when the Churches were told by a Prophet that there was a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine comming, they made a collection, a treaſure, a ſtock for the poore againſt the time of famine, and ſent to them; ſo that it is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unlawfull for a man to care for the time to come. But it muſt have theſe three cautions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 When things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the future, cannot be had but for the preſent.</note> Firſt, there muſt be caring for the future, when thoſe things that are neceſſary
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153805:16"/> and convenient for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot ſo well be had after, as they may for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Hence is the care of the Ant and Piſmire. The Ant layes up in ſummer for win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: becauſe then it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; neceſſary food can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee had in winter. So <hi>Ioſeph</hi> treaſured up in the yeeres of plenty becauſe in famine nothing neceſſary, or convenient could be had.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 When it is without diſtruſting Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</note> Secondly, there muſt be no diſtruſtfulneſſe; no care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the future out of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt of the providence of God, and therfore not over abundant laying up for the time to come; not to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to fence in all places; to ſtop all holes, to prevent all poſſibility of hazard and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153805:17"/> trouble, wee are not thus to diſtruſt the providence of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 When o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsities are not neglected.</note> Thirdly, we muſt not care for the future as to neglect the preſent neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our brethren: wee muſt not ſo lay up for the time to come, as that we care not how it be with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and neighbours, thoſe that wee have relation to, or dwell with. This is the careing for to morrow that overchargeth the heart; when there is careing for the future, When there is care for exceſſe and ſuperfluities; for more than is convenient: when things may bee done as well after as now, yet wee will doe it now. When there is diſtruſt of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153805:17"/> the providence of God that men care not how much they lay up againſt the time to come, Or by what neglect of theſe whoſe neceſſities they ſhould ſupply. This is the ſecond ſymptome, when the heart takes up this kind of care for to morrow, as well as to day; for the time to come as well as for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; that heart is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 When it hinders care of better things.</note> Thirdly, the third ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of being overcharged with care is when there is ſo much care for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and conveniences of this life, as that there cannot be ſo much care for other things as God requiers. Then a man hath eaten too much when he is diſabled to doe the other workes of nature
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153805:18"/> or of his calling. So when a man takes ſo much care for the things of this life that hee cannot care ſo much for God as for them; that he cannot care ſo much for his ſoule as for them; that he cannot care for his family as he ſhould, not for the poore as he ſhould: when men cannot diſcharge that care that lies on them towards all others for the care they have of their owne neceſaries, this care is a great deale too much, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.32</note> 
               <hi>I would have you without carefulneſſe,</hi> that is, without being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with carefullneſſe, <note place="margin">1 To be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice.</note> 
               <hi>He that is unmarried cares for the things of the Lord; but he that is married cares for the things of the world.</hi> It is the argument by which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153805:18"/> the Apoſtle would perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them if other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to keepe from marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; the reaſon is this, becauſe in the ſtate of marriage wee are over much ready to care too much to pleaſe husband or wife, and prouide for our family, and we care ſo much that we care not to pleaſe the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle makes it not a ſinne for married perſons to pleaſe one another; but this is the ſinne they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall into, to overcharge their hearts with that care, and ſo to pleaſe the Lord too little: therefore if other things concurre keeping from marriage keepes from this inconvenience, pleaſing of men more then God. So that care overchargeth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153805:19"/> when there cannot be ſo much care for the Lord as the Lord requireth, and is due to him. Thus when care for neceſſaries cauſeth diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lord: when there is ſuch care for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsities of this life, that the Lord cannot be worſhipped and ſerved without diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here is too much care. In 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.35.</note> 
               <hi>that ye may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the Lord without diſtraction.</hi> When your care is ſo much for food, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for wife and husband, and children, and family, that you cannot attend on the worſhip and ſervice of the Lord without diſtraction, your hearts are overcharged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 To neglect Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> So when you are made to neglect the worſhip of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153805:19"/> and to ſlight that ſervice, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for matter or for the manner of it that is due to God, this much care is too much for this life. The wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath to be gone that they might ſell Corne; It is obſervable they were people that had ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they would not trade upon the Sabbath day, there was ſome Religion and conſcience: but their hearts were overcharged with the cares of this life; for why; they were diſtracted, and weary of the Sabbath: Oh that the Sabbath were gone that we might be get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of money to provide neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>So we find it was the fault of <hi>Martha</hi> in <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. <note place="margin">Iohn 10.</note> ſhee was carefull to provide
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153805:20"/> conveniences for the invite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhee over charged her heart with care as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by this, becauſe ſhee did not give attendance to the Sermon and Doctrine of Chriſt: <hi>Martha, Martha, thou cumbreſt thy ſelfe with many things.</hi> The thing in it ſelfe is lawfull, and convenient: but they overcharge thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for they take thee off from that attention that <hi>Mary</hi> lends to my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>This alſo is that in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31. <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.31</note> 
               <hi>they come to thee, and ſit before thee as my people, they heare thy words, but they will not doe them.</hi> They at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the worſhip of God, they frequent his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, they give eare to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153805:20"/> Sermon, yet they obſerve not to doe the things that thou preacheſt: why ſo? Their hearts are after their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, their hearts are careing for the things of this life, and they are diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in my worſhip, they doe not give that attention, and ſubjection to thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as they ſhould. So this is a ſigne that a mans heart is overcharged. In <hi>Luke</hi> 12.13. <note place="margin">Luke 12.13.</note> Chriſt was preaching, and on a ſudden a man in the company breakes out, <hi>Maſter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I pray thee ſpeake to my brother to divide the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Here was care for the things of this life: but this mans heart was overcharged with this care. How doth it appeare? by this, becauſe he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153805:21"/> did not give ſo much atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to Chriſts preaching, but even then his thoughts were upon worldly things. So when there is ſo much care for the things of this life, that better things are vnder-val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, as <hi>Eſau</hi> for a meſſe of pottage ſells his birth-right: ſo when the heart is ſpent with the cares of this life that the heart is dulled, and deaded, &amp; ſtraitned, &amp; made untoward, and unſerviceable, and weary in the ſervice, and worſhip of God. Any of theſe wayes, when wee cannot care ſo much for God, for the glory of God, for the worſhip, and ſervice of God, in the matter, and manner of it as God requiers; when it is ſo, the heart is overcharged.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153805:21"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 When we neglect the care of our own ſouls.</note> And as it is thus when we cannot care ſo much as wee ſhould for God, ſo when we cannot care ſo much as wee ſhould for our owne ſoules. When people ſo much care for the neceſſaries of this life, that they cannot allow their ſoules the time they ſhould have to build them up in knowledge and grace; for private prayer, for ſelfe examination and confeſsion, for reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and meditation: when there is ſo much care for the things of this life, that we cannot have ſo much as is fit for our ſouls, that heart is overcharged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 When o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are neglected.</note> And ſo for others, when there is ſo much care for our owne neceſſaries, that we doe not care for the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153805:22"/> ſoules of our families; we do not care to inſtruct them, to Catechize them, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and exhort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove them, to diſcharge all duties of our families to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards children, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then alſo the care of neceſſaries overchageth us. Then a man hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his ſtomach with drinke when he hath taken ſo much that he reeles: then a man hath overcharged his back with a burthen when he cannot walke upright, but ſtaggers in his way: and then the heart is overcharged with too much care and thought for neceſſaries, when we cannot uprightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our duties in all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. This is the third ſymptome when the heart is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153805:22"/> ſo charged with the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this life, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Care ſo much for others as ſhe ſhould, not for God, nor our owne ſoules, and for others, and our families as we ſhould.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 When we uſe unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means</note> The fourth ſymptome of a heart overcharged with care, is when the heart ſo cares for the things of this life, that it breakes out into the uſe of unlawfull meanes. Or cannot ſtay Gods lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>When we break out into unlawfull meanes; As when a man deſires ſo to thrive, and his wife and children, that he makes no conſcience of fraud and deceit of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and over-reaching. A lawfull care is ever content with lawfull meanes: and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153805:23"/> that care that makes a man now and then break out into unlawfull meanes, is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the time, when men ſo care to provide ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſaries for this life, that they cannot ſtay Gods time, but they muſt have it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently within ſuch a time, or elſe they will waite no longer. In 2. <hi>King</hi> 6. <note place="margin">2. King. 6.</note> That King, when there was a great famine; he did ſo care for ſupply of neceſſarie and convenient food: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the prophet bid him waite a while, and made him ſtay longer then he would have done, he breaks out, It is <hi>of the Lord, why ſhould I waite any longer?</hi> He would take his owne courſe, and uſe his owne meanes,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153805:23"/> he would no longer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant upon God. This man over-charged his heart with neceſſaries; he cared too much, becauſe he would not ſtay patiently till Gods time was to give him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 When it hinders thought of judgement</note> Fiftly, the laſt ſigne, and evidence of a heart over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, is when the heart ſo cares for the things of this preſent life, that it cannot take in the thought of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and calamities that have beene threatned (to the place where he lives) in the word, and by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: when the heart is ſo ſolicitous about meate, and drinke, and providing for himſelfe, and his family that it thinks not at all of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153805:24"/> threatned by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Or elſe doth not think of them as they ſhould to prepare themſelves, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect calamities comming. This eſpecially is Chriſts meaning in the text: <hi>Take heed leſt your hearts be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with cares.</hi> How ſhall I know that? If that day come upon me unawares then it is an overcharging thought for neceſſaries. When the judgements you are told of, are out of your mindes, or ſo little regarded, that you prepare not; but ſuddenly unawares judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes upon you. This is that overcharging care that is charged upon the old world, and upon Sodome, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.26.30. <note place="margin">Luke 17.26.30.</note> 
               <hi>they are charged that they did eate and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153805:24"/> drink and were over charged with pleaſures. They builded and planted,</hi> there was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging with Care. Care is lawfull in it ſelfe: but they cared too much for theſe lawfull things. And it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by this they ſo min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded providing of neceſſaries, and getting of conveniencies for themſelves and others, that they utterly forgate, or never fitted themſelves for the judgements they were forewarned of. Then in the laſt place you may know whether your hearts be overcharged with care or no. If you finde you are ſo carefull, and take ſuch thought what you ſhall eat, and what you ſhall drinke, and how you ſhall be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, how you ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153805:25"/> for your families, and children, as that you either thinke not of judgements threatned, or are not ſo mindfull of them, or not carefull to prepare for them. By theſe five ſymptomes you may know, whether your hearts be overcharged with care or no.</p>
            <p>Now then the ſumme of the Doctrine comes to thus much; how ever care and diligence be very lawfull for things neceſſary, and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; ſo that it be without diſtraction, and oppreſsion of our ſpirits: Either with diſtruſtfull care for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or perplexity of heart with feare of want for the time to come: Or ſo that it be not careing for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as well as to day, ſinfully
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153805:25"/> for the time to come as well as the time preſent: And ſo that there be not ſo much care for neceſſaries that wee cannot give other things their due care: and ſo that there be not ſo much care that we uſe unlawfull means, that we cannot wait Gods time, or think of judgements threatned: though a care that hath not theſe flawes in it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and comendable; and the more diligent and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and the more carefull, the more commendable. Yet for people ſo to care for the things of this life ſolicitouſly, as to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, &amp;c. This is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the heart: and they that would not have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come unprepared
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153805:26"/> they muſt be carefull that they doe not over charge their hearts thus. Thus the doctrine is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>For the proofe of it, it lies in the text: <hi>Matt</hi> 6. <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Take no thought for too mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> directly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it to us, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>The end of all things is at hand be therefore ſober.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, if you deſire to be prepared for the end that is come then be ſober, ſober in pleaſures, not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with ſurfitting and drunkenneſſe, ſober in Care even of neceſſaries, <hi>be not overcharged with the cares of this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it enough for people to be carefull that they be not overcharged
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153805:26"/> ſometimes, but they muſt be carefull that at no time their hearts be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any of theſe cares.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is playne, becauſe the time of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may come at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y time, at the morning, at evening, at noone-day, or at midnight; and it is vncertaine when the time of judgement ſhall be. And it is certaine that Chriſt ſhall then come to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when people leaſt of all expect him. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all theſe things, who ever would not have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnt to take them una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, muſt take heed that their hearts bee not over charged with the cares of this life.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153805:27"/>
            <p>To come to application,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe 1. inſtruction</note> Firſt, This doctrine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves for inſtruction, to teach us two leſſons,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that take care for abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</note> Friſt, How exceedingly they erre that ouercharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with care for abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, with care for ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie. If it be ſo great an errour to ouercharge the heart with care for neceſſaries, how great an errour is it to charge the heart with care for ſuperfluities? If it be a great errour to care too much for neceſſaries, how great an errour is it to care too much for too much? Yet notwithſtanding this is the errour of theſe times, and of this City Men never content themſelves, they never have enough. It may be ſaid of a great many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153805:27"/> (that are yet profeſſors of the Goſpell) as <hi>Habak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuk</hi> ſpeakes of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> he tranſgreſſeth by wine, there is overcharging of the heart with pleaſures, <hi>he is a proud man, he keepes not at home, he inlargeth his deſire as hell, and as death: he cannot be ſatiſfied. He ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to him all nations, and heapeth to him all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have a generation in this Citie, they are never ſatiſfied, but as ſo many horſe-leeches they cry give, give: they gather to them all the trade and cuſtome, they would if they could gather together all the wealth of the City, and of the Kingdome: Thoſe that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.10. <note place="margin">Pro. 1.10.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153805:28"/> 
               <hi>That are gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of gaine.</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.22. <hi>They make haſte to be rich;</hi> and not only care for neceſſaries, but for too much, for abundance. This muſt needs be an intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able errour, when it is ſo great a fault for a man, too much to care for that which is neceſſary and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Thoſe that take care for unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things.</note> The ſecond inſtruction is to ſhew us how great an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour it is to care for unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things too much. If it be ſo great a fault to care ſo much for things lawfull, how great is it to care for things unlawfull? This is the fault of many ſinners that <hi>drinke iniquity as water,</hi> that never have their bellies ſull enough, <hi>that draw ſinne as with Cart-ropes;</hi> that gallop
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153805:28"/> in the wayes of rebellion: and as <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth, think it ſtrange that others alſo doe not runne with them in the ſame exceſſe of riot. Theſe are the inſtructions that wee may collect hence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion to ſuch as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharge themſelves with care.</note> The ſecond uſe is a uſe of reprehenſion, namely to all ſuch, as over-charge their hearts with care for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life. Such of you as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex your ſpirits with care, that lay ſo much care upon your ſoules, that your hearts ſtoop under it; ſuch of you as take too much thought for the time to come, as care ſo much for the things of this life, that you give not God his due care, nor your owne ſoules, nor your families their due care; ſuch of you as care ſo much how to feed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153805:29"/> your bellies, and to cloath your backs, and to provide for your familie, that you doe not uſe Gods meanes, nor ſtay Gods times, nor have no leiſure to think of, and prepare for thoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have been long threatned: To you I ſpeak; you are ſharply to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. It was Chriſts charge upon all his Diſciples, that they ſhould take heed that at no time their hearts were overcharged with care: your hearts are overcharged, you demeane not your ſelves as the Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Miſtake me not, I blame not them that overcharge their hearts with caring for too much, that are groſly covetous, that belongs to another place; but ſuch as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153805:29"/> overcharge their hearts for things neceſſary, convenient things, that might bee cared for; only they are not to be cared for too much. You are the perſons that I ſpeak of, you that overcharge your hearts for food, and rayment, and convenient things: let me tell you, this caring too much for things neceſſary, is as truly covetouſneſſe, as the care for other things. Covetouſneſſe is not only a deſire of too much; but it is alſo covetouſneſſe when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart too much deſires any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utward thing. Not only he is covetous that cares for too much, but he that too much cares for neceſſaries. That his is ſo, we ſee it plaine in <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.24,25. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>No man can ſerve two maſters, hee cannot
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153805:30"/> ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> Will you not ſay, hee is covetous that ſerves Mammon, and not God? hee that makes mammon his God? Obſerve Chriſts inference in the next verſe, <hi>Therefore I ſay, take no thought,</hi> no overcharge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought, <hi>take not thought for your life, what you ſhall eat and drink.</hi> Doth not the connexion of the words imply, that hee that takes thought for his life, that is, too much care, that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth himſelfe with care though it bee but for his life and livelihood, hee ſerves mammon, and is covetous?</p>
            <p>So in Luke 12.13.15. <note place="margin">Luke 12.13.15.</note> there a man breaks out, and deſires Chriſt to ſpeak to his brother to divide the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: this was but a lawfull
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153805:30"/> care; a man may care for his inheritance, and for the equall diviſion of it, and for peace between him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are joynt-heires of it; the care is not unlawfull, it is a thing neceſſary: yet notwithſtanding you ſhall finde that Chriſt upon this very mans action, he exhorts againſt covetouſneſſe. After hee had anſwered the man and checked him, verſe 14. in the fifteenth verſe, <hi>take heed of covetouſneſſe.</hi> What was the occaſion hee breaks off his Sermon, and exhorts his Diſciples and others from covetouſneſſe? becauſe this man ſpeaks to Chriſt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the inheritance: Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us that that mans caring too much for thoſe things that in themſeves were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153805:31"/> and convenient, was as truly covetouſneſſe, as if he had cared for too much.</p>
            <p>Conſider this, when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple overcharge their hearts with c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, it is as truly cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe as they that care for too much. That you may alſo gather from, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>Let your converſation bee without Covetouſneſſe.</hi> I, but what is that? <hi>be content with ſuch things as you have:</hi> for hee hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> The words ſeem to imply a double covetouſneſſe. Firſt, deſire not ſuperfluities; <hi>be content with what you have.</hi> Secondly, doe not too anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly charge your hearts with neceſſaries, for the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>I will never faile thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> This teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153805:31"/> that is brought an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the error in the heart, the care for neceſſaryes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the other, the care for ſuperfluityes.</p>
            <p>By this we may learne that it is coveteouſneſſe, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the heart with care for neceſſaryes. And indeed it muſt needs bee ſo; for it is evident, there is a love of mony: if there were not a love of mony, as mony, thou wouldeſt never care more for that then for God, and grace, and the keeping of a good conſcience. If thy ſoule did prize God, and grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mony, and above the neceſſaryes of this preſent world, thou wouldeſt have enough, ſo thou couldeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy them: and ſo thy deſires and cares would be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153805:32"/> to other things. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is an evident ſigne, when the ſoule cares too much, though for neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that that ſoule is immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in its deſires.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, whereſoever there is immoderate care, there is immoderate deſire: Care is the fruit, they that care too much, deſire too much. Where there is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate deſire, there is a corrupt opinion: where a man deſires a thing too much hee hath too high an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that thing. Well, thou that careſt too much for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryes, thou deſireſt them too much, and thinkeſt too highly of them: thy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is poyſoned, thy judgement corrupted, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Principles keepe the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153805:32"/> ſterne of thy ſoule, and act it aſwell as the ſoules of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If thou didſt not think too highly of mony, and of the neceſſaryes of this life, thou wouldeſt never deſire them too much, or care too much for them. It is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigne, where any ſoule cares for the things and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryes of this world, they thinke too highly of the God of the world, <hi>Money.</hi> If thou didſt not think that money were a good thing, thou wouldeſt never deſire it too much. If thou didſt not think that a mans life conſiſted in theſe things, thou wouldeſt neuer bee too carefull for theſe things. If thou didſt not care more for having the things, than for uſing of the things of this world, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153805:33"/> account for the things of this world, thou wouldeſt never deſire, or care for them too much. In a word, if thou wert not deeply guilty of Ignorance, and unbeleife, if thou wert not Ignorant of the alſufficiency, of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, and providence of God; or diſtruſt in the all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, and faithfulneſſe, and providence of God, thou wouldeſt never overcare, thou wouldeſt never over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy ſoule with the cares of this preſent life. Therefore you ſhall finde that Chriſt in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.30. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.30.</note> 
               <hi>If God ſo cloath the graſſe of the feild, ſhall he not much more you, O yee of little faith?</hi> they that care too much for food and rayment are of little faith, if of any.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153805:33"/>
            <p>Therefore apply it to your ſelves, ſuch as are guilty in this, of caring too much, and overcharging your harts with caring for the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of this life; know your fault, and errour, you are guilty of coveteouſnes; that very ſin that the ſcripture ſo much condemnes. Thou art guilty of that ſin that the Apoſtle calls <hi>Idolatry Coll.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Coveteoſneſſe which is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> A coveteous man makes an Idoll of his mony; hee makes it his God: why ſo? hee ſets his heart upon it, his hope and confidence, his truſt, his love, and deſire, and joy is upon his mony: Therefore coveteouſneſſe is Idolatry. In a meaſure thou art guilty of this, thou put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt too much hope, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153805:34"/> and deſire, and joy upon outward proviſion of neceſſaries, or elſe thou wouldeſt never care too much for them, thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt never over-charge thy heart with care, if thy heart did not pitch too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe outward things.</p>
            <p>Covetouſneſſe is that ſin that the Apoſtle would have Chriſtians to ſeparate from. All ſuch as profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are covetous, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.11.</note> If any that is called a brother be covetous, <hi>Eat not with ſuch a one.</hi> Covetouſnes is ſuch a ſin as habitually reigning in the ſoule, and a man dying in that eſtate, it ſhuts him out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.</note> This is the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of covetouſneſſe, and this thy ſoule is tainted with, that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153805:34"/> art overcharged with the cares of this preſent life.</p>
            <p>And beloved, if you bee Gods people (I put this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, becauſe it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the children of God may be tainted this way, to overcharge their ſoules with the cares of this life) if thou bee one of Gods, and art overcharged with care, thy ſin is not the leſſe, but the greater: It is a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, a ſurffetting: thy ſoule is a glutton, a drunkard, that is overcharged with cares. Now what a ſhame is it for thee to be drunke, to be overcharged with cares, that art not of the night, and of the darkneſſe, but art a childe of the day? How doth S. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſon, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>They that are drunk, are drunk
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153805:35"/> in the night,</hi> though now drunkards be ſhameleſſe: yet in thoſe times men that were drunke, would be drunke in the night, that they might not be ſeene, that their ſhame might not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly knowne; that was the faſhion of theſe times: there was more modeſty and ſhame then, than in our times: But, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>You that are of the light and of the day,</hi> &amp;c. that is, as it is a great deale more ſhame to be drunk in the day than in the night, becauſe more eyes ſee a man, and look on him; there are more that take notice of his folly: ſo it is more ſhame for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to be overcharged with cares, than for worldlings: they are children of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153805:35"/> night, and of the darkneſſe; there is none minds them, or looks for other things at their hands. But Chriſtians are in the light, nay they are lights, Cities ſet on a hil; and if a Chriſtian be drunk with cares, every one ſees his ſhame, his reeling, his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and reproach; all the world takes notice of him. Therefore if you be the people of God, and hope you are, and yet finde your hearts overcharged, the more is your ſhame, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that you are of the day.</p>
            <p>Nay, the more is your ſhame, becauſe you have eares to heare; and you have often heard, the Lord hath warned you of the day of judgement, which for ought we know, ſhould
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153805:36"/> have come upon us long ere now; if not nationall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet God might have ſummoned thee by any of that that is paſt, to the great day of judgement; and thou haſt been told, that the day of judgement ſhall come ere thou art aware; and yet thou that haſt had eares to heare theſe inſtructions, ſhouldeſt thou bee unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and unfitted for the day of judgement? ſo long as thy heart is overcharged with cares, thou art unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If that judgement ſhould come, then thou wouldeſt be tooke napping, thou wouldeſt be unfitted. This ſerves for the ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of thoſe that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their hearts with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153805:36"/> cares. So much for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with cares</note> The third uſe now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, that is a uſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, that is, that you looke to your ſelves, leſt at any time you be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with cares; leſt this evill of covetouſneſſe prevaile upon you. Covetouſneſſe is that that we are all prone to, <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.13. <note place="margin">We are all prone to it, Ier. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>From the greateſt to the leaſt, they are all given to covetouſneſſe.</hi> Great men, they are prone to covet too much; and poore men are prone too much to covet things neceſſary. One way or other we are generally addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to covetouſnes, all ſorts, all kinds of us. Even Gods own people are prone to this errour, therfore <hi>David</hi> prays againſt it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.36. <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.36.</note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153805:37"/> my heart to thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and not to covetouſneſſe,</hi> Would <hi>David</hi> have prayed againſt the bending of his heart to covetouſneſſe, if he had not found himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined that way? Therefore wee ſee our Saviour Chriſt here exhorts his Diſciples to take heed of being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with cares; this he would never have done, if they had not been prone to have beene overcharged as well as others. So <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> a man that was more than ordinarily moderate, yet 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10,11. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.10,11.</note> 
               <hi>Thou, O man of God, flee theſe things:</hi> What things? The love of money, and the coveting of that evill covetouſneſſe; do thou looke to thy ſelfe, to flee theſe things.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:153805:37"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">We are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to it.</note> As we are all prone to this errour, to have our hearts overcharged, and ſo tainted with this evill covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo we are ſtrongly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to it. It is not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, or ordinary bent of ſpirit in us all this way, but more than an ordinary ſtrong bent of ſpirit. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you ſhall finde our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15. <note place="margin">Luk. 12.15:</note> 
               <hi>Take heed, and beware of covetouſneſſe.</hi> He addes a double caution, <hi>take heed, and beware of it,</hi> ſee to it, watch and ward, the words imply both; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way with heart and hand look to your ſelves, that your hearts be not overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with this evill of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. Therefore in <hi>Matth</hi> 6.25. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.25.</note> to the end of the Chapter, Chriſt three
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153805:38"/> times in thoſe few verſes, doth repeat one and the ſame exhortation, which is that I now give you, that you take no thought what you ſhall eat or drinke, or wherewith you ſhall be cloathed. Three times our Saviour exhorts his Diſciples to take heed of being overcharged with cares for the neceſſaries and conveniences of this preſent life. And why all this, but becauſe there is a ſtrong, &amp; a more than ordinary inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bent of ſpirit, to this overcharging of the heart?</p>
            <p>The devill, it may be, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not draw many of us to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet too much, to that <hi>pleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexy,</hi> and ſuperabundant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the things of this world, but yet eaſily hee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153805:38"/> drawes us too much to covet thoſe things that ſeeme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and convenient: Eſpecially, beloved, is this exhortation ſeaſonable and uſefull in this time, wherein the Lord leads many of his children into ſtraights and neceſſities, and brings them, as he did once his firſt-borne Iſrael, to the wilderneſſe, and exerciſeth them with the want of thoſe things that ſeeme neceſſary and convenient. In theſe times, and for ſuch as are exerciſed with theſe ſtraits, this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is ſeaſonable, and much to bee liſtned to, that you take heed, that your hearts bee not overcharged with care for the things of this life.</p>
            <p>To overcharge the heart
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153805:39"/> with care, <note place="margin">Overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging care, a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> is to bring upon us a kinde of puniſhment to puniſh our ſelves. We need not wiſh a greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to an enimie, then to be overcharged with care. It is a perplexing diſquieting thing, therefore in <hi>Ezek</hi> 12.18,19. the Lord threatneth it as a judgement upon peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <note place="margin">Ezek. 12.18,19.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall eat their bread with carefulneſſe, and drinke their drinke with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">It makes men mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</note> The heart being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care, makes the ſpirit prone to commit that great ſin of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites in the wilderneſſe, to repine and murmure againſt the Lord, to tempt and limit the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael.</hi> For what was the ground of their oft falling into that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153805:39"/> great ſinne of murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and tempting him? It was this, they were over-carefull for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries of this preſent life: they were over-carefull for bread and water, and for fleſh: they ſo overcharged their hearts with care for thoſe neceſſaries, that their ſpirits failed and murmured againſt God; they limited God, and tempted the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> as the ſtory records.</p>
            <p>This inordinate, too much care for the things of this life, is a branch of that love of money, that is the root of all evill. <note place="margin">It is the root of moſt ſins.</note> It is the ſeed, not of murmuring onely, but even a wombe that is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bring forth almoſt any ſinne againſt the Lord.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153805:40"/>
               <note place="margin">It hinders grace.</note> It is one of the greateſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers &amp; coolers of grace, and of holy and ſpirituall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that is. Water is not more contrary to fire, than this over-caring heart for worldly things, is to grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And the meanes of grace.</note> You ſhall ſee how it keeps men much from the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and meanes of grace, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.16,18,19. <note place="margin">Luke 14.16.18.19.</note> Chriſt he cals them to the means of grace expreſſed under the parable of a man that <hi>made a great ſupper, and bade many.</hi> Chriſt invites people to the meanes of grace, but the cares of this life, when they care too much for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of this life, keeps them that they come not; they all with one conſent began to make excuſe: What made them keep from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153805:40"/> comming? The one ſaid, <hi>I have bought ground, and I muſt needs goe ſee it:</hi> Another ſaid, <hi>I have bought five yoke of oxen, and I muſt goe prove them.</hi> Theſe were lawfull and neceſſary things that their care was about, for a man to look to his ground, to try his oxen: but they over-cared for theſe things; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could not finde time and leaſure to come to the means of grace.</p>
            <p>And put the caſe people ſhould come to the meanes of grace, yet notwithſtanding where the heart is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care, the means of grace are unfruitfull, and ineffectuall; if not altogether, yet ſo, as that they bring nor forth <hi>fruit to perfection, Luk</hi> 8.14. <note place="margin">Luk. 8.14.</note> The third ground
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153805:41"/> brought not forth fruit to perfection: why ſo? <hi>It was choaked with the cares of this preſent life.</hi> A heart over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care, is kept from preparing to heare the Word; it cannot before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditate, and conſider, and ponder, and pray, and the like. When it comes into the preſence of the Lord, where his word is preached, it cannot be attent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; for the heart is after covetouſnes, diſtracted with care and thought about this and that; ſo it cals off the minde, that it cannot lend that attention, at leaſt, give that intention of minde to the Word, as is needfull.</p>
            <p>After, it cannot ſo medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on that Word; it hath not that leaſure and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153805:41"/> to recall the Word, to conſider it, to apply it. Nay, hardly can it beleeve the certainty, the truth, and promiſes of the Word. Thus I ſay, the heart overcharged with care, if it keep not from comming to the meanes, yet from receiving benefit by the meanes; if not from all benefit, yet from ſo much profit as is needfull to bring forth fruit to perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">It pierceth the heart.</note> In a word, the overcharging the heart with cares, is as it were a piercing the ſoule through with many darts, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>The love of money is the root of all evill, which while ſome covet after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row with many ſorrowes.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153805:42"/> darts goe into the ſoule of that man or woman that is overcharged with care. And in this reſpect, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, our Saviour compares cares to thornes, becauſe they choak, and prick, and pierce the ſoule.</p>
            <p>But I cannot better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to this duty, to take heed of being overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with care, then in our Saviours words and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who preached a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon this very purpoſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.25:</note> to the end of the Chapter, there is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation laid downe that I now give, <hi>Take no thought,</hi> be not overcharged with care, not for neceſſaries for life, <hi>What you ſhall eat or drink;</hi> or for the body, <hi>What you ſhall put on:</hi> And you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153805:42"/> ſhall finde divers arguments, <note place="margin">Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt too much care.</note> whereby Chriſt preſſeth this exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 God hath given bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things without our care.</note> The firſt argument is in the end of <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Is not life more than meat? and the body than rayment?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, God, without your care, hath given you the better, and doe you not think, that without immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate care, he will give you the worſe? what care did you take for life? yet God hath given it you; What care did you take for a body before you had it? yet God hath given it you. If God hath given you the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without care, life, &amp; a body, will not God give that which is of leſſe worth, with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate care, namely, meanes to preſerve the life, and to cover the body? There is the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:153805:43"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 The Lord provides for mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> The ſecond argument is in <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>Behold the fowles of the ayre, they ſow not, they reap not, they gather not into barnes, and yet your heavenly father feedeth them; are you not much better than they?</hi> And this argument is repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>verſ.</hi> 28, 29, 30. <hi>Why take you thought for raiment? con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Lillies of the field how they grow, they toile not, they ſpin not, and yet I ſay, Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of theſe: Wherefore if God ſo cloath the graſſe of the field, that to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the oven, ſhall hee not much more you, O yee of little faith?</hi> The ſumme of the argument comes to thus much, The Lord provides for meaner creatures, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153805:43"/> are of leſſe worth and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with him, without their care and perplexing of themſelves with care. If God take care for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner creatures, will he not provide for you that are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler creatures, of more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and eſteeme with him, without your perplexing of your ſelves with care? What care doe the Lillies take for themſelves? or the fowles of the aire for themſelves? they have no means at all to provide for their being, or for their well-being; they take no thought or care at all; they have no meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may provide for themſelves; yet for all this they never want, God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for them. If God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for them, which in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153805:44"/> compariſon of you are but baſe creatures; the graſſe that to day is, and is gone to morrow; you are laſting creatures, your ſoules are immortall, your bodies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure longer than the graſſe; though they may die, yet they ſhall be raiſed againe. Doth God then take care for them that are ſo inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to you in worth, and that have no kinde of meanes of proviſion of neceſſaries for themſelves at all; and doe you not thinke that the Lord will care for you that are better, to whom he hath given ſome meanes and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of helping yourſelves? There is the ſecond argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much care uſeleſſe.</note> The third argument is laid down, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Which of you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153805:44"/> by taking thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can adde one cubit to his ſtature?</hi> This is taken from the uſeleſneſſe of our care, that is, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging care, diſtracting care. Let a man care never ſo long, and break his heart with care, what good can it doe? can he help himſelfe with one bit of bread, or with one drop of water, with the meaneſt covering for himſelfe, with all his cark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing care? No more than a man by his care can make a gray haire black; or by his care can make his deformed body ſtraight; or by his care can make his low body tall: no more can a man by diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting care help himſelfe with any neceſſaries in the leaſt meaſure. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127. <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.</note> Riches come from God, <hi>It
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153805:45"/> is in vaine for man to riſe early, and to eat the bread of carefulneſſe:</hi> God gives wealth, and he alone; <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. <note place="margin">Prov. 22.</note> 
               <hi>The poore and the rich meet together, and God is the maker of them both.</hi> No more than a man can make himſelfe, can a poore man make himſelfe rich, or a rich man make himſelfe richer, God makes them both. There is no ſillier thing in the world than for men to diſtract themſelves with care; all the fruit of it is this, they wound their hearts, and diſtract their ſpirits, and doe not the leaſt good to themſelves, no not in the point wherein they care.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Overmuch care hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> Nay, not onely this care is uſeleſſe, it helps nothing;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153805:45"/> but it is prejudiciall, it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders much. To uſe the means lawfully that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that is our worke; but the addition, the effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the thing by the meanes, that is Gods work. If we doe thing aright, doe our taske, we muſt uſe the meanes, and leave the iſſue to God: But when we take that upon us that belongs to God, and not onely uſe the meanes, but oppreſſe our ſelves with care, about the event and ſucceſſe; God with-holds the ſucceſſe, that elſe he would give to the uſe of the meanes: and becauſe we perplex our ſelves with care about things, therefore God many times with-holds the things. This is the third argument.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153805:46"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Overmuch care uſed by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</note> Againe, the fourth argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is laid downe, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>For after all theſe things doe the Gentiles ſeek.</hi> The people of God muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like heathens, they muſt not overcharge their hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout neceſſaries; Chriſtians muſt not doe ſo. <hi>But thou, O man of God, flee theſe things.</hi> Chriſtians are men of God: There he ſpeaks in a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all relation, becauſe he was a miniſter: but it is true in generall; wee are men of God, we muſt not doe as the heathens doe. They that know not God, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and better things, they overcharge their hearts with care for neceſſaries. It is a ſhame for Chriſtians to be like heathens, to be hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as eagerly after the things
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153805:46"/> of this world, as heathens.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 GOD knowes our wants.</note> The laſt Argument is in the end of verſe 32. <hi>your he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father knoweth that you have need of all theſe things.</hi> The Argument ſtands thus; It is a folly for children that have a father, a father that knoweth their neceſſityes, that is able to ſupply their neceſſityes, that is ready and willing to miniſter accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their need, it is folly for them to perplex them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e about neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. So for Chriſtians, they have a father, why ſhould they then oppreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with care? They have a father that is better able then earthly fathers; for he is an heavenly father. They have a father that knowes their neceſſityes, that knowes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153805:47"/> better than they doe that they need food and rayment, that is able, and willing, and ready to do it: Then for theſe children of God to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe themſelves with care, is to charge God, as if hee were not a father, or not a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving father, or not knowing, or not an able father. It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers either a great deale of Ignorance of God, or of the relation we ſtand in to God, or elſe a great deale of Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in thy opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God. Whenſoever the heart is overcharged, and diſtracted with cares, it is as much, as if a man ſhould proclaime to the world, I have a father that knows not my need, that cares not for it, or minds it not, or is not able to ſupply it. Theſe are the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153805:47"/> by which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour preſſeth this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I am now upon, <hi>that ye at no time be overcharged with cares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Means to keep from overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging care.</note> But it may bee askt, by what meanes ſhall we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to come to fence our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that we be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care about the neceſſaries of this life.</p>
            <p>The meanes are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I To worke our carnall principles.</note> Firſt, to work out of your minds thoſe carnal Principles that make your hearts prone this way; and to poſſeſſe your minds with thoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Principles, that may eaſe your hearts of this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging care. Care, as you heard before, is the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to ſomewhat; or the earneſt bending of the mind
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153805:48"/> to obtain ſomething: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according as the mind is Principled, ſo lightly it is ordered for care. That as the ſhip is ordered as the Pilot pleaſeth; ſo the mind in point of care is ordered by that Principle, that is in the minde: If therfore there be a Principle in the minde that preſents the neceſſaries of this life over-deſirable, then the mind muſt needs be over-carefull. If there be a Principle that preſents the neceſſities of this life in a right manner, then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the minde is rightly on theſe things; and ſo is not overcharged with cares.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaks of a double minded man, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.8. Therfore men are
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153805:48"/> double minded, becauſe they are double Principled: there are ſome Principles in the mind, that preſent theſe outward things, as moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable; therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thoſe men are moſt for the world, moſt for ſin. There are ſome things that preſent God, and the things of God, as moſt deſireable; therefore ſometimes (it may be for a fit) they are moſt for God, and moſt for grace. The double mindedneſſe comes from the contrariety of the Principles, that are ſtrong and prevalent in the minde: That look, as in a ſhip, if there be two contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pilots, and one would carry the ſhip one way, and the other another; when one Pilot prevailes, the ſhip
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153805:49"/> is ordered this way; when the other prevailes, it is ordered the other way. Double mindedneſſe comes from contrary principles, that both at ſeverall times work. Then the firſt means to prevent the heart from being overcharged with care, is to diſpoſſeſſe the minde, to work out ſuch carnall Principles as make the minde care for neceſſaries too much; and to work in contrary Principles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. 1 That outward things are abſolutely good.</note> As for inſtance, one car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Principle to be wrought out of the heart, that it be not overcharged with cares, is this: That principle that is intimated, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4,5. <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4,5.</note> 
               <hi>Who will ſhew us any good.</hi> This Principle, that theſe things
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153805:49"/> are a good, an abſolute good, wherein there is a true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and happineſſe to be ſound: this is a Principle in moſt mens minds, and a root of overcharging the heart with care.</p>
            <p>It is true, theſe outward things are the good bleſſings of God; but notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in themſelves they are not a good; that is, not ſuch a good as miniſters any true contentment, as yeelds any true happineſſe to the ſpirit: Therefore we ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, many have theſe things, and yet they want contentment, they are moſt miſerable: Many want theſe things, and yet they have contentment, and are moſt happy. Here is the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple you muſt ſet your
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153805:50"/> ſelves againſt that over-high conceit of the things of this life, as if there were in them an abſolute goodneſſe, the fountaine of contentment and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 That wee cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy our life without them.</note> A ſecond principle to be rooted out of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it is this; that there is no enjoying our life without the poſſeſſing of theſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. This was that, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled the Jewes in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe: they had this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that they lived by bread, and water, and fleſh; and if they had not preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of theſe outward ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, they muſt needs die preſently: therefore when they wanted bread they fall a murmuring, <hi>Would God we had died in Egypt.</hi> And when they wanted wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153805:50"/> 
               <hi>Would we had died in Egypt:</hi> And <hi>were there not graves enough there to bury us, that the Lord hath brought us into the wilderneſſe to ſlay us?</hi> Whence came this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging care? becauſe of this Principle, they thought if they did not poſſeſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to maintaine them, they could not be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Get this principle out of your minds. Therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that rule that Chriſt gives, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. <note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> 
               <hi>A mans life conſiſts not in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of outward things he poſſeſſeth:</hi> No nor in the competencie; a mans life ſtands not in food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>We ſee the children of Iſrael lived, and might have come to <hi>Canaan,</hi> had it not
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153805:51"/> beene for their murmuring: however they were alwayes exerciſed with the want of theſe neceſſaries, yet they were preſerved and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. That was a leſſon that the Lord ſet himſelfe to teach his Church, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3. <note place="margin">Deut. 8.3.</note> All the forty yeares that God led them about the wilderneſſe, was to teach them that leſſon, contrary to this Principle; he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them, and led them about, to teach them, that <hi>Man lives not by bread only, but by every word that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the mouth of God.</hi> That is a ſecond princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that muſt be wrought out.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 That a certainty is a great benefit.</note> A third Principle that we muſt diſpoſſeſſe our minds of, is this, that there is a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153805:51"/> great benefit by a certainty, and by having a competency, and conveniency of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for this preſent life. This conceit runs in moſt folks thoughts, that there is a great deale of benefit by having a certainty of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proviſion, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petencie, that we be not in ſtraits, and put upon depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; this is a Principle, and a falſe one. Indeed it cannot be denied, but that where God gives a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we have cauſe to thanke him; where he gives a new dependance, and provides a competencie, we have cauſe to bleſſe him. Yet there is no ſuch great matter in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, or in having a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for a certainty;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153805:52"/>
               <note place="margin">No cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in this world.</note> when thou haſt got a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, what haſt thou got? where is this certainty? Is it in this world that thou poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeſt ſo much goods and money, and lands, is this a certainty? I ſay there is no certainty in this world. All that is under the Moone, is more changeable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine than the Moone. As ſoon maiſt thou periſh for want of neceſſaries, that haſt a certainty, as they that have none at all. Doe not men as often periſh as beaſts, and birds, and Lillies, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty at all, no, not for the next day? There is nothing certaine here. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23 6. <note place="margin">Prov. 23.6.</note> 
               <hi>Why wilt thou ſet thy heart upon that which is not, riches? take the wings of an Eagle,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153805:52"/> and flee away:</hi> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo uncertain as theſe things, that when we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe we thinke are certaine. So for competency; thou thinkeſt it is excellent to have proviſion of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency. But conſider, when God ſets himſelf to bring up his own Church, as it were in an immediate manner, God brought them up with out preſent proviſion of a competencie. The children of Iſrael, that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods firſt born, his dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: he had newly fetched them out of the fire, and his affection was then ſtrongeſt towards them; yet what was Gods manner of dealing with them, when he ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to do them good, and to prepare them for <hi>Canaan</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:153805:53"/> he gave them not an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent eſtate and ſupply of proviſion, and competency; no, they were faine every day to depend on God for bread and water, and ſo he exerciſed them.</p>
            <p>Beloved, great advantage comes by a dependent eſtate upon God; I confeſs through the ſinfulneſſe of man, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are many inconveniences in depending upon men: but to depend on God, which we ſhould doe, whether we have a competency, or no, there are many Benefits come by this dependance, by not having a certain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Proviſion. Many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of the love of God, of the power of God, of the providence of God, of the truth of God, of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153805:53"/> mercy of God, doe they get that are not furniſhed with a competency every way. Therfore I ſay, work out this principle alſo, for it is a very falſe one. I give but ſome inſtances, by which you may ſee what I mean. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver principle you finde that makes the heart prone to take too much care for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries; take care to work out that principle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 To poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the heart with ſpirituall principles</note> Againe, as you muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe the minde of theſe principles; ſo labour to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the minde with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary principles, ſuch ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall principles as the Word affords us, that we may fence our hearts againſt overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging care. To inſtance ſome of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, root in you that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153805:54"/> Principle of Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <note place="margin">Of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> that there is a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, a certain all-ſufficient Providence. That this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence reacheth to all things that God hath made, and in a ſpeciall manner to mankinde. Poſſeſſe the ſoule with this Principle; <note place="margin">It is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall.</note> God he is <hi>a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Creator;</hi> that is, he after he hath made the Creature, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts not the Creature. The Carpenter builds a houſe, but never takes care for it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; God doth not ſo, he is a faithfull Creator ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> that is, after he hath made the creature, he hath a care of the creature, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully watcheth over it, and holds it in his hand to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: And therefore the School-men well call, and expreſſe the providence of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153805:54"/> God by this name and term; the holding of things in his hand. This is the nature of God, he holds all things in his hand that he hath made: <hi>My Father,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.</note> 
               <hi>worketh hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> God did not ceaſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he ceaſed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but he worketh hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Then he ceaſed the work of creation; but hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he worketh the work of providence; God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things that he hath made. God upholdeth all things that he hath made. God provides for all things he hath made. God orders all things he hath made, to that proper end himſelf hath appointed them to. There is a providence of God, a certain providence.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:153805:55"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Vniverſall</note> It is grounded upon the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of God, for he is a <hi>faithfull Creator.</hi> The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God is univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall to all things he hath made, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. The Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, not only of the garden, but thoſe of the field: The birds, not only in the cage, but in the ayre: the beaſts of the wilderneſſe; God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for all: for Sparrows, for Ravens, for Lions. His providence is over all things; it is an all-ſufficient providence; it is fully able to uphold &amp; provide for all. That providence is the ſame that made all; the ſame love, the ſame goodneſſe, the ſame wiſdome, the ſame power that made all, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, provides for all: it is therefore an all-ſufficient providence.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:153805:55"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Eſpecially to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</note> Nay, it is a providence that is eſpecially to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. The goodneſſe of God, and the love of God, hath mankinde for its ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all object. Therefore the providence of God alſo hath mankinde, even all mankinde, for a ſpeciall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Now then conſidering all theſe things, what need the heart be overcharged with care, when we have one ſo able, and ſo faithfull to care for us. So ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Caſt your care on God, for he careth for you:</hi> what need we then perplex our ſelves with care? Thus root our ſelves in this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the doctrine of Gods providence: ſtudy this, and be throughly grounded in it.</p>
            <p>And to help this, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153805:56"/> of the paſſages of divine providence, whereby God hath provided neceſſaries for mankinde. How did the Lord provide for the widdow? he ſent <hi>Eliah</hi> to her: <hi>Eliah</hi> comes to her, and askes her ſomething to eat; Alas, ſaith ſhe, <hi>I have nothing but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle oyle, and a little meale, and I am gathering two ſticks, that I may make a cake for my ſon and I, and then eat it, and die.</hi> She was now at the laſt, ſhe had no more to ſave her own life, and her childs life; and in this nick of time, the Lord ſends <hi>Eliah</hi> to multiply the meale and the oyle, till the famine were ended.</p>
            <p>How did the Lord after provide for <hi>Eliah</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, when he ran away and hid himſelf, that the Lord
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153805:56"/> checked him himſelf; he was there through his own error &amp; default, yet the Lord made the Ravens to feed him.</p>
            <p>How did the Lord provide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Rochel,</hi> in the ſiege before this laſt fatall ſiege, when they were ready to be famiſhed, by making a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of fiſhes to come &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver themſelves up into their hands, that were never there before, nor never ſince, and to abide till the ſiege were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. There are many paſſages of Gods providence, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by ordinary means, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by extraordinary; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lord ſhewes, that he cares for us, and will not ſuffer us to want, if we caſt our care on him. This is the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; we ſhould be poſſeſt ſtrongly of this, that God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153805:57"/> provides and cares for us.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Gods co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</note> Secondly, poſſeſſe our ſelves of this, that God by promiſe hath bound himſelf to provide neceſſaries. If we be his people, and in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God, not onely the providence, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, ties him to provide whatſoever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient. The new Covenant wherein the Lord hath tied himſelfe to pardon our ſins, to ſubdue our iniquities, to ſanctifie our natures, in that very Covenant the Lord hath tied himſelfe to furniſh us with all outward conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, as we read, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. to the end of the Chapter. There are three branches of it, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Sanctification, and the ſupply of all neceſſaries.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153805:57"/> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſes of this life, and of that which is to come.</hi> God is tied by his Word, and by his oath; he is bound by that Covenant that is ratified by the Bloud of Chriſt, that is ſealed by the Sacraments of the New Teſtament; God in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is tied as well to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for our bodies as our ſoules: he is the God of our bodies, as well as of our ſoules: Chriſt died for our bodies, as well as for our ſoules: he hath undertaken for our bodies, as well as for our ſouls: and every time we receive the Sacrament, we receive the Seale of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, wherein God is tied to provide neceſſaries for us</p>
            <p>Thereupon Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren never want enough, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:153805:58"/> they have faith enough to depend on God. God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtayes his hand in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, till there come enough for his children. Therefore in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> when God rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons up the things he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on <hi>David, I gave thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Kingdomes of Iſrael and Iudah, and thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſes and wives, and if that had not been enough, I would have given thee more.</hi> Whereſoever God ſtayes his hand in the diſtribution of outward things, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is enough for that man or woman. This is the ſecond Principle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Outward things not to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for, but expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> The third Principle which we ſhould poſſeſſe our minds with, is, that the outward neceſſities of this preſent
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:153805:58"/> life, they are not properly to be cared for, but to bee waited for; they are not to be taken thought for, but to be expected. So Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.32,33. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.32,33.</note> 
               <hi>Seek the Kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and other things ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> I pray obſerve it, Seek heavenly things, expect out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things; labour for the one, look for the other.</p>
            <p>This is the rule that God gives us concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things; we are not ſo. much properly to care for them, as to caſt our care upon God for them; for ſo you ſhall finde, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4 <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.4.</note> 
               <hi>Roul thy ſelfe upon the Lord, commit thy way to the Lord, truſt in him, and he will bring it to paſſe.</hi> We are to caſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153805:59"/> our care for outward things upon God, and to expect and wait for the things from God, and not ſtrictly to care for them, to toyle and drudge, and labour for them.</p>
            <p>Not (beloved) that wee muſt be idle: <hi>he that doth not labour, muſt not eat.</hi> We muſt uſe the means that God hath appointed, ſo as God hath appointed: what means God hath appointed for the getting of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means, we muſt uſe, and no other means: but uſe them ſo as God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, without diſtracting cares, without perplexing cares. We muſt uſe lawfull means lawfully, but not expect the things from the means, or by the means, but uſe the means in obedience to God.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153805:59"/> And having uſed the means, we muſt look for the things from God; this is the rule of Chriſtians; this is the way whereby God would have us ſeek for the neceſſaries of this preſent life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. <hi>Rowle thy ſelfe on God;</hi> truſt in him, having uſed the means, becauſe God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them. Then truſt to God for a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, pray to God for them, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <hi>Being carefull in nothing, but in all things make your requeſts known to God.</hi> This is the third Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple wherewith we ſhould poſſeſſe our minds; outward things are rather to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, than cared for: wee muſt uſe the means, and caſt our care for them upon the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:153805:60"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 The ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard that comes by outward things.</note> Again, a fourth Principle is this, (poſſeſſe your minds with this Principle) that there is more hazard and trouble comes to us by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying theſe outward things, than benefit: the care about the right uſe of them, about the improving of them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the account that is to to be given for them, is more than the benefit that comes by them. This in other things makes men not affect ſome kinde of offices. A Steward in a houſe hath money enough, he hath it in his own power to diſpoſe, but yet becauſe he is a Steward, and muſt give an account of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry penny, many wiſe men had rather be without the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards purſe and place, than have the trouble and the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153805:60"/> hazard of the account of it. If you conſider this, you would not ſo much care for the things of this life: If you did remember what ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard there is in the uſe, and in the improvement, and in the account that muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Chriſtians are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of all things.</note> Laſtly, in the fifth place, poſſeſſe your minds of this Principle, if you be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, you cannot but be rich, you cannot but be poſſeſſors of all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. <hi>All things are yours, for yee are Chriſts.</hi> So in <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.5. <hi>God hath choſen the poore of the world to be rich in faith, and heirs of the Kingdome.</hi> And in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>As poore, yet making many rich; as having nothing, yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> Thou art a Chriſtian, thou art the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153805:61"/> poſſeſſor of all things, the Lord of all things: thou canſt not but be rich, and in the beſt things, in faith, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God. What needeſt thou charge thy heart with care? Here is the firſt means to be uſed, to keep the heart from being overcharged with care. Study theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and work out the other. Conſider them, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them, meditate on them, that your ſoules may be act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them. This is the firſt means.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond means, to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a preſent condition.</note> The ſecond means is; To be content with our preſent condition. Whatſoever we have, be content with it: This is the means the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture preſcribes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Let your converſation be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out covetouſneſſe:</hi> Covet not
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153805:61"/> too much, neither too much covet any thing. But how ſhall this be attained? in the next words, <hi>Be content with ſuch things as you have:</hi> what your preſent condition is, be contented with it. Though you be in ſtraits and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, though you be worſe than your neighbours, be content with your preſent condition, and then you will never overcharge your hearts too much. For the overcharging the heart with too much care, comes from overmuch deſire; and overmuch deſire comes from want of contentment. Therefore men deſire much, becauſe they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that that they have. Therefore labour to be content with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153805:62"/> condition, whatſoever it be.</p>
            <p>And to perſwade this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that all, whatſoever we have or enjoy, is freely given us of God; there is nothing due, nothing deſerved. And we are angry with thoſe beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, that are not content with our allowance, when we give them freely; nay, if we give them nothing at all.</p>
            <p>Againe, It is the will of God, that thou ſhouldeſt be as thou art; it is Gods doing, it is Gods decree &amp; appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is his will, &amp; we pray, That the will of God may be done; ſhall we not then be content when the will of God is known? Whatſoever thy condition be, that thou art thus, and thus, in never ſuch ſtraits, by the effect of it, it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:153805:62"/> is plain, it is the appointment of God from eternity, that thou ſhouldeſt be ſo. Now the will of God is known, therefore be content, ſeeing thou prayeſt it may be done. This is the ſecond means.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exerciſe faith.</note> The third means is, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Why take you thought, oh ye of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith.</hi> It is want of faith, or want of the uſe of faith, or weakneſſe of faith, that cauſeth the heart to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care; labour therefore to get faith, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to exerciſe faith. They have it of faith, and the uſe of faith is one of the moſt notable means to preſerve the ſoule from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with care. Faith in the providence, and in the promiſes of God; faith in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153805:63"/> the power of God, faith in the wiſdome of God; the acting of faith in theſe things, preſerves the ſoul from being overcharged; the reaſon is, becauſe faith quiets the heart in the want of any thing, by making it ſure, and making it preſent. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Faith is the evidence of things not ſeene.</hi> Thou wanteſt meat, thou wanteſt drink, thou wanteſt proviſion for thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; faith will make meat and drink, and proviſion of neceſſaries evident to thee: though they be not ſeene, faith will make them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to thee. Faith in Gods providence, in Gods power, and truth, and goodneſſe, and the like; theſe make preſent thoſe things thou wanteſt, and theſe will keepe thee
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153805:63"/> from care. Faith gives a man aſſurance of the things in due time and meaſure, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the mean time it makes the heart quiet and content, and careleſſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, labour for faith. We muſt live by faith (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) not onely in regard of our ſoules, but in regard of our bodies: not onely in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the world to come, but in the buſineſſe of this preſent world. In all things live by faith, walk by faith, doe every thing by faith, or elſe it is impoſſible to keep the heart from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged. That is the third means.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Turn care another way.</note> The fourth means of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heart from being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged, is to turn thy care another way. It is the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153805:64"/> practiſe of ſome, when men bleed too much at the noſe, to open a vein, and draw the bloud to another current, they turn the bloud and ſtop it; and it is a notable means to keep the heart from care of the things of this life, when we grow more in care for the things of another: For therefore the heart is too carefull for this life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is too careleſſe for a better life. The ſtream can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not run ſtrongly two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wayes; and the heart of a man or woman cannot run ſtrongly to heaven and earth. Seek thou ſtrongly the things above, and thou ſhalt never too ſtrongly ſeek the things below. Therefore in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.36. <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.36.</note> 
               <hi>Incline not my heart to covetouſneſſe:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153805:64"/> how ſhall that be? <hi>Incline my heart to thy teſtimonies, and not to covetouſneſſe.</hi> Be carefull of Gods teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and thou ſhalt not be overcarefull for the things of this life. <hi>But thou, O man of God, flee theſe things,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.11.</note> Flee covetouſneſſe: how is it done? follow after righteouſneſſe, hunt after it, purſue it, grow eager after the things of God, and of a better life, and thou ſhalt be moderate to the things of this life: therfore oft think of the betterneſſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things above earthly, and outward things. The things of God are a great deale more neceſſary than the things of this preſent life. Grace is more neceſſary than the poſſeſſion of meat, or
<pb facs="tcp:153805:65"/> means to get meat, and drink, and apparell. Thou canſt not be happy without grace, thou maiſt be happy in the want of all theſe; theſe are not neceſſary, the other are; theſe are not certain, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are; theſe are not ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the other are; theſe cannot bring grace, grace will bring theſe. Whatſoever Principles there are to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large thy deſire, and increaſe thy care for the things of God, poſſeſſe thy ſoule of them, and turn the ſtreame ſtrongly upward, and it will be weak downward.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves with outward things.</note> A fifth means is, take heed of tangling our ſelves as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as may be in any thing in this world: whatſoever it be in outward neceſſaries, in outward conveniences, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
<pb facs="tcp:153805:65"/> your ſelves as little as may be in any. It is a ſtrange thing to ſee what a ſecret power there is in any thing in this world, to draw our hearts too much after them. We cannot touch pitch but we ſhall be defiled; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meddle with any thing in this world, but we are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be over ſhoos, and over boots, (as the Proverb ſaith) in it. Therefore ſince there is ſuch a bewitching in all the things of this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld, keep from them as much as is poſſible.</p>
            <p>Vpon this ground, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.32</note> the Apoſtle perſwades them not to marry, without ſimple neceſſity; and his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is given, becauſe <hi>I would have you with out carefulneſſe,</hi> that is, without overcharge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:153805:66"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:153805:66"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:153805:67"/> care; as if he ſhould ſay, it is impoſſible almoſt for the heart to meddle with any of the things of this life, but we ſhall care to much; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it may be without greater inconvenience, keep from marriage: for however the cares of marriage be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet notwithſtanding when you are in thoſe things, it is hard not to care too much: ſo we may ſay of any thing elſe; as much as we can, let us keep our ſelves free. They wrong their ſoules in worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and affaires, that care not how deep they dive in thoſe things; it is impoſſible they ſhould keep from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcharged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6 To caſt our care on God.</note> The laſt means whereby we may be kept from over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153805:67"/> care, is, as ſoon as we perceive our hearts to be burdened with care, that it growes a little too ſtrong for us, preſently we begin to eaſe our backs of it. Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome not yourſelves to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the burden of care, but as ſoon as by the former ſignes you find they begin to grow heavie, caſt them off; turn your thoughts upon thoſe things that may kill and cure this care.</p>
            <p>Nay, let us caſt our care upon God: that as a wiſe man, as ſoon as he perceives a burden that he carries is too ſtrong for him, if there be another that is able to bear it, he wil preſently eaſe his own back, and lay it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his friend: ſo, as ſoon as thou findeſt thy heart begin
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153805:68"/> to be burdened with care, take it at the firſt, eaſe thy ſelfe of it at the firſt. God is ready and well pleaſed when thou caſteſt thy care upon him: it is the very command of God (as wee ſee before) that we ſhould caſt our care upon him. God would have you without care, therefore at the firſt, before overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging care have got to great a vent, and hath had too long a cuſtome upon thy ſoule; at the firſt labour to caſt it upon the Lord.</p>
            <p>As it is with the body, when the humours have took to a head in one place, and finde a vent there, it is a hard thing to turn them: ſo if thy ſoule be accuſtomed to beare the burden of care, to be overcharged with care,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153805:68"/> thou wilt find it a hard thing to turn them off thy back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; it will grow to thy back. It is not with this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as it is with other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; when a man carries a burden never ſo long, it is as looſe as at the firſt, and no weightier; but there is a double inconvenience in cares; care, if it lie long, growes to the back: for care is to the ſoule, as weeds in the naturall ſoile, wherein they grow, rooted, and the longer they ſtay, the bigger they grow: ſo care will grow to the ſoule, and it will be impoſſible almoſt to remove it; and the longer it lies on, the more it increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the ſtronger it growes: And therefore at the firſt, as ſoon as you perceive care to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153805:69"/> overcharge you, that there is more care than there ſhould be, that it begins to burden your ſpirits, disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your ſoules, caſt your care upon the Lord: as ſoon as you perceive care to ſinke your ſpirits, go to God, and caſt it upon his back. The way how that is done, you heard before.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by uſing the means he hath appointed, but as his means.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by truſting in God for the eaſing you of that burden.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by making known your requeſts to the Lord; <hi>Be carefull in nothing:</hi> how ſhall that be? <hi>In all things make known your requeſts:</hi> tell God of your burdens, make known your cares, and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153805:69"/> when you have done ſo, with confidence lay them on him, and eaſe your own ſpirits. If thus you take your ſelves at the firſt, when care op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth you, it will be eaſie to disburden your ſpirits; if once you be accuſtomed to bear this burden, it will be ſo rooted in you, and lie ſo hard on you, that you can ſcarcely remove it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſum of the Text.</note> The ſumme of all the Text is this, I told you that theſe verſes were a direction that Chriſt gave to his Diſciples againſt the times of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either univerſall, the end of the world, or elſe any nationall judgement what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: <note place="margin">The time of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known.</note> It is a direction to them how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they might not be prejudiced in the day of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153805:70"/> vengeance, and in the time of calamity. Firſt, Chriſt layes down two grounds on which he faſteneth his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; the one ground is fetched out of <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.44. <note place="margin">Mat. 24.44</note> where there is the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation that is here, <hi>In ſuch an houre as you think not, the ſonne of man ſhall come:</hi> there is one doctrine; that the time of judgement ſhall come when it is leaſt thought of, when people leaſt expect it. Another ground, which was the reaſon of this, is that <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.35. <note place="margin">Luk. 21.35.</note> 
               <hi>For as a ſnare ſhall it come upon the face of the earth.</hi> The time of judgement ſhall come as a ſnare, as a full, unavoidable deſtruction to the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. That is the reaſon that the coming of judgement is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153805:70"/> unknown, and brought upon the earth in a time when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple think not of it, becauſe it is to be a ſnare to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality. Theſe are the two doctrines that Chriſt la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s down, as the ground of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Therefore we ſhould be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> Vpon this ſuppoſition, that the time of judgement ſhall come unknown, when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple leaſt think of it; and therefore it ſhall ſo come, becauſe it ſhall be a ſnare to catch the generality in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable deſtruction. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the exhortation of Chriſt to his Diſciples, and to us, is this, that we be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.44. <note place="margin">Mat. 24.44</note> 
               <hi>be yee ready:</hi> and in <hi>Luke</hi> 21. verſe 36. <note place="margin">Luk. 21.36.</note> 
               <hi>Watch and pray alwayes.</hi> Here is the exhortation that he gives: conſidering theſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:153805:71"/> things, his counſell to his people is this, that they be alway ready, alway watch, and alway pray.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, what.</note> Firſt, that they be ready alway, it ſtands in two things: Having all needfull graces, and having the uſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of them. It is not enough to have all graces; but to uſe and exerciſe them. The grace of faith, the grace of love, the grace of hope, the grace of repentance, the grace of uprightneſſe; an ability to every duty, in our generall and particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; a zeal after every good work; theſe are the graces that muſt be had. It is not enough to have theſe, but we muſt be in the exerciſe and uſe of theſe. This is to be ready.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:153805:71"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To watch alway, what.</note> Again, to watch, there muſt be a keeping from ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſlumber, and a heeding our ſelves in all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, leſt we be overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Doctrine and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that alwayes foregoe times of judgement; there muſt be a watching in all things, and in all times.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To pray alway, what.</note> Thirdly, praying alway; that is, firſt of all a praying oft upon all times, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and opportunities we can pick out.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſtant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in times appointed, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and evening, and the like.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, inſtant, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed prayer, not to give over praying, acording as we have command and opportunity. This is the duty that Chriſt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:153805:72"/> teacheth all his Diſciples, conſidering that the time of judgement ſhall come una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, when people leaſt look for it, and as a ſnare; therefore it is wiſdome for his people alway to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, alway to be watching, alway to be praying.</p>
            <p>Now to the end they may be able to do this, he exhorts them to take heed of being overcharged. A man that is overcharged with meat and drink, he cannot watch, he cannot diſcharge his duty and office. So it is with the ſpirits of people that are overcharged, they cannot watch and pray, and ſo the time of judgement may come upon them unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and unawares. They muſt take heed of being
<pb facs="tcp:153805:72"/> overcharged, whether with the pleaſures of this life, lawfull or ſinfull. And alſo with the care, even for the neceſſaries and conveniences of this preſent life. This is the wiſdome that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt taught his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, concerning the latter times: and this is the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that in them Chriſt taught you: And this is the wiſdome that in theſe times you muſt labour to practiſe. We have great cauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Chriſts comming to judgement in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: he hath warned us of it beyond Sea, by late fearfull experience. We ſee all Gods wrath beyond Sea is not yet quenched, it hath broken out fearfully, and of late worſe than ever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153805:73"/> the times of judgement are comming, the times you have long heard of, and that ſhall come in a time that is leaſt thought of. When this land leaſt thinks of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it ſhall come; for it ſhall come as a ſnare to the generality; therefore if you have eares, hear what the Lord ſaith; therefore be alway ready, watch and pray. Which that you may doe, take heed that you be not overcharged with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and contentments, and cares of this life. Thus much for this Text.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153805:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
